<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Cevuru plates of Amma I</title><!--ALT TITLE: "-->
        
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoding</resp>
          <persName ref="part:daba"><forename>Dániel</forename><surname>Balogh</surname></persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>intellectual authorship of edition</resp>
          <persName ref="part:daba">
            <forename>Dániel</forename>
            <surname>Balogh</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>DHARMA <note>This project has received funding from the European Research
          Council (ERC) under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and
          innovation programme (grant agreement no 809994).</note>
        </authority>
        <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
        <idno type="filename">CalE36-Cevuru-Amma1</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported
              Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit
              https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to
              Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View,
              California, 94041, USA.</p>
            <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Dániel Balogh.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc><!-- only the handDesc can be filled in at this stage -->
        <msDesc><!-- //// NB: the msIdentifier had to be added for validation purposes ///. It will be edited later with the metadata spreadsheet -->
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
            <idno/><!-- don't modify this -->
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents><!-- describe the intellectual content of an inscription -->
            <summary><!-- //// NOT MANDATORY  ////--></summary> <!-- offers the possibility to give a summary of the inscription's content -->
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <handDesc>
              <p>Halantas resemble the regular consonants in their principal part, but have no headmark; instead, a sinuous line is attached to their top right, resembling a tilde with the right-hand end extended upward into a repha-like vertical stroke (possibly with a headmark there). It is my impression that this extension is a stylisation of the was subscript consonants are attached to primary consonants in conjuncts, with the implication that a character incorporating this stroke is attached to a non-akṣara. The body of M has a reduced body resembling an archaic ma but definitely different from the standard ma in this script, e.g. l3 pādānudhyātānāM. (In l34, phalaM is not quite clear but seems to have a much reduced body.) The body of N is like regular na, but slightly smaller, e.g. l22 ārādhitavāN.</p>
              <p>Original punctuation marks are short, plain, raised vertical bars extending from head height down to about median height or above. The one after phalaM in l34 seems not to be raised but to float at median height.</p>
              <p>Other palaeographic observations. Anusvāra is at headline height to the right of the akṣara to which it belongs, e.g. l1 śrīmatāṁ. It is separated from its akṣara by a line break in l16-17 kuṭu/ṁbinas; Chhabra refers to E Cālukya parallels in ll 29-30 of the <ref target="CalE21-Reyuru-Visnuvardhana2.xml">Reyūru grant of Viṣṇuvardhana II</ref> (where, however, the dot in question may be something other than an anusvāra), and ll 61-62 of the Masulipatam plates of Amma <!--CHECK probably CalE49, add ref when encoded.-->. The stroke for medial e sometimes bends to the right and up, attached to the top of the consonant on the left (l20 sāhasena, l22 saṁpṛtair). In addition to these, Chhabra points out as unusual the o in l1 sagotrāṇāṁ, but I see nothing striking in it; Chhabra's point may be that the left-hand stroke in this case curls down and back to touch the body of the consonant. Subscript l (e.g. l6 vallabhendrasya, l16 guṇakkenallā°) is a simplified spiral continuing to the right in a notched horizontal line, then attached upward to the body of the main consonant. It sort of reminds me of the way halanta consonants are formed in this script, with what could be a halanta l turned 90 degrees to the right. </p>
                <!-- The script name(s) will be inserted here at a later stage from the metadata spreasheet. At this stage, you can mention here in a free-text paragraph any characteristics of the writing observed more than once in this inscription that seem unusual/uncommon or otherwise noteworthy given the general characteristics of the script in question. See EG 11.2. -->
              <!-- If you need to identify individual hands (EG §7.5/) in addition to one or more paragraphs of general palaeographic description, wrap <summary> around the <p> or <p>s above, and, outside <summary>, create <handNote> elements for each hand as follows:
                <summary><p><p/></summary>
                <handNote xml:id="Pallava00001_hand1"></handNote>
                <handNote xml:id="Pallava00001_hand2"></handNote>
              -->

           </handDesc>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="part:daba" when="2020-08-24" status="draft">Initial encoding of the file</change>
      <!-- Add a <change> entry for each significant change to the file. -->
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:space="preserve">
    <body>
      
<div type="edition" xml:lang="san-Latn">
<div type="textpart" n="A"><head xml:lang="eng">Seal</head>
  <ab><lb n="1"/>śrī-tribhuvanāṁkuśa</ab>
</div>
<div type="textpart" n="B"><head xml:lang="eng">Plates</head>
<pb n="1r"/>
<p><pb 

n="1v"/><lb 
n="1"/>svasti<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied> śrīmatāṁ sakala-bhuvana-saṁstūyamāna-mānavya-sagotrānāṁ <lb 
n="2"/>hārīti-putrāṇāṁ kauśikī-vara-prasāda-labdha-rājyānāṁ mātr̥-gaṇa-pari<lb 
n="3" break="no"/>pālitānāṁ svāmi-mahāsena-pādānudhyātānāM bhagavan-nārāyaṇa<lb 
n="4" break="no"/>-prasāda-sa<space type="binding-hole"/>māsādita-vara-varāha-lāñchanekṣaṇa-kṣaṇa-vaśīkr̥tā<lb 
n="5" break="no"/>rāti-ma<space type="binding-hole"/>ṇḍalānām aśvamedhāvabhr̥tha-snāna-pavitrīkr̥ta-vapu<lb 
n="6" break="no"/>ṣāṁ cālukyā<space type="binding-hole"/>nāṁ kulam alaṁkariṣṇoḥ satyāśraya-vallabhendrasya
kula-tila<lb 
n="7" break="no"/>kāyamāna-svāsi-dhārā-namita-ripu-nr̥pati-makuṭa-taṭa-ghaṭita-maṇi-mayū<lb 
n="8" break="no"/>kha-puṁja-piṁjarita-pāda-padma-yugalasya cālukya-bhīma-bhūpālasya pautraḥ
<lb 
n="9"/>sāsi-sannahana-sva-tanu-tulā-tulita-bhūri-bhāra-bhāsura-hema-rā<choice><orig>s</orig><reg>ś</reg></choice>i-mahā<pb 

n="2r" break="no"/><lb 
n="10" break="no"/>dāna-viśeṣā<choice><sic>ḍ</sic><corr>ḍh</corr></choice>yīkr̥ta-vipra-kula-kalpavr̥kṣasya samasta-bhuvanāśra<lb 
n="11" break="no"/>ya-vijayādityasya putraḥ Amma-mahīpatir ggaṇḍaragaṇḍo rājamahe<lb 
n="12" break="no"/>ndra Iti vikhyātaḥ dāyāda-timirodyad-dinakara-kiraṇāyamāna-bhāsurā<lb 
n="13" break="no"/>si-sanāthī<space type="binding-hole"/>kr̥ta<surplus>ta</surplus>-dakṣiṇa-<choice><sic>bh</sic><corr>b</corr></choice>āhus sa<surplus>sa</surplus>rvva-lokāśraya-śrī-viṣṇuva<lb 
n="14" break="no"/>rddhana-mahā<space type="binding-hole"/>rājādhirāja-parameśvara-paramabhaṭṭārakaḥ parama-mā<lb 
n="15" break="no"/>heśvaraḥ gu<space type="binding-hole"/>dravāra-viṣaya-nivāsino rāṣṭrakūṭa-pramukhān kuṭu<lb 
n="16" break="no"/>ṁbinas samāhūyettham ājñāpayati<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied></p>
<p>viditam astu vaḥ guṇakkenallā<lb 
n="17" break="no"/>para-nāmadheya-vijayāditya-mahārāja-prasādīkr̥ta-hasty-āroha<lb 
n="18" break="no"/>ṇāvāpta-gudravāra-viṣaya-śrīmad-umikili-nāma-grāma-rāṣṭrakūṭa<pb 

n="2v" break="no"/><lb 
n="19" break="no"/>-m<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>hātmyasya konakula-candeyarājasya pautraḥ rājādityānuja-mano<lb 
n="20" break="no"/>hitāryyasya putraḥ vemarājo nāma subhaṭaḥ sāhasena kali<lb 
n="21" break="no"/>-yuga-<choice><sic>s</sic><corr>ś</corr></choice>ūdrako mat-pitaraṁ vijayāditya<supplied reason="omitted">ṁ</supplied> baddha-karppaṭakaḥ svāmi-bhakti<lb 
n="22" break="no"/>r ārādhitavāN<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied> tad-ārādhana-svāmi-bhakti-saṁp<choice><sic>r̥</sic><corr>rī</corr></choice>tair asmābhiḥ kumāra-vija<lb 
n="23" break="no"/>yādityā<space type="binding-hole"/>nna-prā<choice><sic>s</sic><corr>ś</corr></choice>ana-nimitte kramāgata-siddhāyāṣṭa-gadyāṇa<lb 
n="24" break="no"/>kaṁ paritya<space type="binding-hole"/>jya sarvva-kara-parihāra<surplus>ṁ</surplus>m umikilī-grāma-grāmaṇīs sa <lb 
n="25"/>vemarāja<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> kr̥taḥ<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied></p>
<p>grāma-dakṣiṇataḥ Ervvoka-cenu<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied> Asyāvadhayaḥ<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied> <lb 
n="26"/>pūrvvataḥ vranta<g type="commaHigh">.</g> dakṣiṇataḥ dūdrupāka-sīmaiva<g type="commaHigh">.</g>
paścimataḥ rāca-cenu <lb 
n="27"/>cāṇḍ<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>la-kṣetraṁ ca<g type="commaHigh">.</g> Uttarataḥ koḍu<g type="commaHigh">.</g></p>
<p>grāmottara-diśi Aypa-Ervvoka-ce<pb 

n="3r" break="no"/><lb 
n="28" break="no"/>nu<g type="commaHigh">.</g> Asyāvadhayaḥ<g type="commaHigh">.</g> pūrvvataḥ koḍu<g type="commaHigh">.</g> dakṣiṇataḥ vanneṟu<g type="commaHigh">.</g> paścimataḥ <lb 
n="29"/>koḍu<g type="commaHigh">.</g> Uttarataḥ kolani mulugu<g type="commaHigh">.</g></p>
<p xml:lang="tel">puṭṭi-nirugu saveraṁ Iruvadinālgu vuṭla-ni<lb 
n="30" break="no"/>ṇḍṟāyam padu-gaṇḍu padeḻ dumu<g type="commaHigh">.</g> tamulaṁmula-tūmeṇḍu<g type="commaHigh">.</g></p>
<p>Asyopari na <lb 
n="31"/>kenacid bā<space type="binding-hole"/>dhā karttavyā<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied> yaḥ karoti sa paṁca-mahā-pātaka-saṁyu<lb 
n="32" break="no"/>kto bhava<space type="binding-hole"/>ti<g type="commaHigh">.</g> tathā ca vyāsenāpy uktaṁ<g type="commaHigh">.</g></p>
<lg n="1" met="anuṣṭubh">
<l n="a">bahubhir vvasudhā dattā</l>
<l n="b">bahu<lb n="33" break="no"/>bhiś cānu<space type="binding-hole"/>pālitā</l>
<l n="c">yasya yasya yadā bhūmis</l>
<l n="d">tasya tasya tadā <lb n="34"/>phalaM<g type="comma">.</g></l>
</lg>
<lg n="2" met="anuṣṭubh">
<l n="a">sva-dattāṁ para-dattāṁ vā</l>
<l n="b">yo hareta vasuṁdharāṁ</l>
<l n="c">ṣaṣṭiṁ varṣa-sa<lb n="35" break="no"/>hasrāṇi</l>
<l n="d">viṣṭhāyāṁ jāyate k<choice><orig>ri</orig><reg>r̥</reg></choice>miḥ</l>
</lg>
<lg n="3" met="āryā">
<l n="ab">veṁgī-maṇḍala-rakṣa<choice><sic>no</sic><corr>ṇa</corr></choice>-bhuja-bala<lb n="36"/>-kaṭakeśvaras samājñāptiḥ</l>
<l n="cd" real="+---+-+--+--++----+">bhaṭṭa-ni<unclear>ravadya-sa</unclear>ntati-bhaṭṭa-mahā<unclear>kāla</unclear>-viracitaṁ</l>
</lg>
<pb n="3v"/>
</div>
</div>
        
        
        
        
        
<div type="apparatus">
  <div type="textpart" n="A"><head xml:lang="eng">Seal</head>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" n="B"><head xml:lang="eng">Plates</head>
   <listApp>
      <app loc="3">
        <lem>-mahāsena-</lem>
        <note>As Chhabra duly notes, there is a superfluous dot high above <foreign>se</foreign>.</note>
      </app>
      <app loc="4">
        <lem>-varāha-</lem>
        <note>As Chhabra duly notes, there is a superfluous dot at mid-height between <foreign>va</foreign> and <foreign>rā</foreign>.</note>
      </app>
      <app loc="13">
        <lem>-sanāthī°</lem>
        <note>According to Chhabra, there is a superfluous dot above <foreign>sa</foreign>. This is not visible in the scanned rubbing.</note>
      </app>
      <app loc="13">
        <lem>sa<surplus>sa</surplus>rvva-</lem>
        <note>As Chabra notes, emendation is not strictly necessary, as the first <foreign>sa</foreign> may be interpreted as a pronoun. I believe a scribal error is more likely.</note>
      </app>
      <app loc="22">
        <lem>-saṁp<choice><sic>r̥</sic><corr>rī</corr></choice>tair</lem>
        <note>As Chhabra points out, <foreign>saṁpr̥ta</foreign> could be derived from the verb <foreign>pr̥ṇoti</foreign>, but this is restricted to Vedic usage and thus the intent here must have been <foreign>saṁprīta</foreign>.</note>
      </app>
      <app loc="26">
        <lem>-sīmaiva<g type="commaHigh">.</g></lem>
        <note>I follow Chhabra's edition, which prints an original punctuation mark here. In the estampage, only a space is visible.</note>
      </app>
      
      
      
      
   </listApp>
  </div>  
  
</div>



<div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" resp="part:daba">
  <div type="textpart" n="A"><head xml:lang="eng">Seal</head>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" n="B"><head xml:lang="eng">Plates</head>
<p n="1-18">
</p>
<p n="47"></p>
  </div>  
</div>



<div type="translation" xml:lang="fra" source="bib:Estienne-Monod2008_01">
  <div type="textpart" n="A"><head xml:lang="eng">Seal</head>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" n="B"><head xml:lang="eng">Plates</head>
<p n="1-18">
</p>
  </div>
</div>




<div type="commentary">
<p>Discovered in Cēvūru village in Kaikalūr tāluk of Kistna District in the Madras Presidency, about 1928, by the villager Polavarapu Ankayya, son of Venkata Reddi, who was digging the debris of a collapsed mud house. Seen there by Chhabra in November 1938 and borrowed for study.</p>
<p>More detail about the term <foreign>karpaṭa</foreign> is found in the Māṁgallu gramt of Amma II<!--CHECK This is CalE48, encode reference when text is encoded.-->. There it is not a military man but a scholar who undertakes <foreign>karpaṭa</foreign> for the sake of the <foreign>rāṣṭrakūṭa</foreign> Kākaṭya Guṇḍyana in order to secure his favour (ll50-52, <foreign>guṇḍyanaṁ vīram uddiśya … yena karppaṭam ābaddhaṁ tat-prasādābhikāṁkṣiṇā</foreign>). The chief in turn grants him a village. This vow (l53, <foreign>karppaṭī-vrata</foreign>) is said there to involve morning baths and chastity, but the wearing of rags is not explicitly mentioned. I assume that this vow was performed with the declared intent that the merit thereby acquired go to the performer's metaphysical stockpile, that it was at the time an established method of acquiring a land grant and/or the position of headman for the performer or his descendants, and that in the present case Vemarāja performed it after retiring from the military. It is also possible that, both here and there, the word is used figuratively in the sense of utterly selfless service.</p>
<p>As Chhabra points out, the last stanza lacks one mora at the end. He suggests <foreign>-bhaṭṭa-mahākāla idam akarot</foreign>. Though metrically correct and appropriate to the context, my preference would be <foreign>-bhaṭṭa-mahākāla-racitam idaṁ</foreign>.</p>
</div>



<div type="bibliography">
  <p>Edited from the original by B. Ch. Chhabra (<bibl rend="omitname"><ptr target="bib:Chhabra1947-1948_02"/></bibl>), with translation and inked rubbings supplied by Hultzsch. Chhabra collaborated with N. Laksminarayan Rao (and, apparently, also with C. R. Krishnamacharlu) for the Telugu part of the inscription. The present edition by Dániel Balogh is based on a collation of Chhabra's text with his facsimiles.</p>
  <listBibl type="primary">
    <bibl n="BCC"><ptr target="bib:Chhabra1947-1948_02"/></bibl><!-- one <bibl/> per item of primary bibliography -->
  </listBibl>
  <listBibl type="secondary">
    <bibl></bibl>
  </listBibl>
</div>

      
      
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
